Guide to the Herbert Finch papers, 1967-1983
Finch, Herbert papers, 1967-1983
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Herbert Finch papers, 1967-1983.
13-6-2182
Herbert Finch
6.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, consultant reports, speeches, articles, master's thesis, Ph.D. dissertation, material from Joyce Hamilton Finch
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Contains personal and professional documentation; correspondence, consultant reports, committee work, organizational memberships and boards, speeches, articles, master's thesis, Ph.D. dissertation, course material and various other items. Also material from Joyce Hamilton Finch, 1930-1991.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Archivist and librarian, Cornell University Library.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Contains personal and professional documentation; correspondence, consultant reports, committee work, organizational memberships and boards, speeches, articles, master's thesis, Ph.D. dissertation, course material and various other items. Also material from Joyce Hamilton Finch, 1930-1991.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Finch, Herbert.; Finch, Joyce H.
Subjects:
Archivists--New York (State); Librarians--New York (State); Regional planning.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal and professional documentation
  Correspondence, consultant reports, committe work, organizational memberships and boards, speeches and articles, master's thesis and Ph.D. dissertation and various other items -- created by C. Herbert Finch, 1931-. Job related material can be found in the "Archives of the Archives," collection accession folders, the Labor Managemnet Documentation Center records and in the administrative records of the Cornell University Library
  - Vita, position classification, change of status, Who's Who (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Management Assn. planning exercise, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Management Assn. planning exercise, including McGrath report, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oral History Manuscript, "A Policy Statement on Academic Archives," with Olivia Narins, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Field Log for University of Kentucky, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Journal, disbounded, 1954-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research Leave Application, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Letter's from Phil's class, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1991-2004 (Box 17)
  - Retirement Letters, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1991-2004 (Box 17)
  - Weekly Calendars, 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1963-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1981-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Boards, Committees and Consultations, 1966-1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Boards, Committees and Consultations, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Boards, Committees and Consultations, 1980-1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - COPAR and City Planning Correspondence, 1966-1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Thesis, 1959, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Loss Prevention Survey Olin Library, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - University Library Committee on Development, 1979-1981 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
- Series II. Material from Joyce Hamilton Finch, 1930-1991
  - Correspondence, 1960-1991 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    Arranged chronologically, including a folder for undated ones. Mostly from the 1980's, they are letters she wrote or received and saved for one reason or another, including the fact that some are original art work
  - Letters, May-June 1991 (Box 12, Folder 4-10)
    Letters written to her by relatives, friends and clients after they learned of her cancer. Since all came within two months, they are arranged alphabetically and the sheets have been numbered for easy reference and order. Those that were "get - well" cards with no personal messages were not saved, but Joyce read all of them -- or they were read to her -- before she died. There is some original art work and some poetry including a poem Joyce wrote for a friend several years ago
    An alphabetical list of correspondents, keyed to the sheet numbers, follows for subseries two and four
    1
    Joyce's letter to her clients
    2
    AAUW
    4
    Louise Adams
    5
    Terre Allen (2)
    8
    Kit and Harlan Banks
    9
    Jean Barnaba and Jean Hope
    10
    Anita Baumann
    11
    Stephanie Belber
    12
    Tom Bennet
    13
    Jonathan Bishop
    14
    Beth Brown
    15
    Betty and Janet Brown
    16
    Joan and David Brumberg
    20
    Les Buchanan
    21
    Jan Butler
    23
    Laurel Butler
    24
    Lynn Cagle
    26
    Ann Calkins
    30
    Linda Caughey (2)
    32
    Diana Finch Chase (6)
    38
    Kathy Ruth Chase
    39
    Bart Conta
    40
    Alice Cook
    41
    Joan Cooke
    42
    Darylen Cote (3)
    48
    Cristopher Cullen
    49
    Mary and David Curtiss
    50
    Sue Dale-Hall
    51
    Elizabeth Delahanty
    52
    Alice Davie
    53
    Gail Davis (2)
    55
    Patty Davis
    56
    Peggy Dunlop
    57
    Ann Dyckman
    58
    Don Eddy
    59
    Howard and Erica Evans
    60
    Susan Eyster
    61
    Cynthia Farbaniec (2)
    64
    Jennie Farey
    65
    David Finch
    66
    Frank and Janice Finch
    67
    Jeff and Angela Finch
    68
    Philip A. Finch (5)
    74
    Trudy Firestone (3)
    80
    Forward Investment Club
    81
    Mary Gaylord
    82
    Christa Gee
    83
    Eleanor Gibson
    84
    Guy and Carole Gresham
    85
    Helen Hamilton
    86
    Virgie Hamilton (4)
    90
    Barbara Hand
    91
    Margaret Hartman
    92
    Bruce Hatch
    93
    Fran Helmstadter
    94
    Marion M. Henderson
    95
    Chris Henke
    97
    Connie Hill
    98
    Dorothy Hill
    99
    Laura Holmberg
    100
    Pat Holmes
    101
    Olka Hood
    102
    Mary Hunt
    103
    Helen Jensen
    104
    Karla Johnson
    107
    Janet and Bart Robinson
    108
    Anne T. Jones
    109
    Judy Jones
    110
    Tom and Elizabeth Kallman
    111
    Mary Lou Kieffer
    112
    Sue and Jud Kilgore
    113
    Louise Kingsbury (2)
    116
    Anne Kinney
    117
    Marian Kira
    118
    Joan and Ray Loehr
    119
    Naomi Lorance (3)
    122
    Sandy Lyons
    123
    Allison and Norm MacLean
    125
    Sibyl Martin
    126
    Tim Martin
    127
    Nancy McGinnies
    128
    Carolyn Miller
    129
    J. Gormely Miller
    130
    Jan Miller
    131
    Nina Miller
    132
    Sue Miller
    133
    Doris Mitchell
    134
    Mirete Mitchell
    136
    Phyllis Moen
    137
    Marty Moesch
    138
    Nancy Moser
    139
    Karl L. Mount
    140
    Mary Beth Norton
    141
    Gay Oliver
    142
    George D. Patte, Jr.
    143
    Edith Poppensiek
    144
    Frances Powers
    145
    Barbara Privett (2)
    147
    Jane and Keith Privett (2)
    150
    Barbara Prudhomme
    153
    Nancy and Andrew Ramage
    154
    Gil Rankin
    155
    Connie Reps
    156
    Ellen Rosten
    157
    Valeta Samuelson
    159
    Edna Shilling
    160
    Shayle and Helen Searle
    161
    Melissa Seigel (2)
    163
    Betsy Shaw (4)
    167
    Ginny Simons (2) [watercolors]
    169
    Carol U. Sisler
    170
    Mary Jane and Willard Speck
    172
    Jim Spero
    173
    June Stone (2)
    175
    June Henry Stone
    176
    Grace Tasker
    Pat
    Tempest
    178
    Peg Thomas (2) [watercolor]
    184
    Berta Unger
    185
    Peg and Barney Unsworth
    186
    Pat Vaughan
    187
    Marjorie Veronneau
    188
    Elva Volbrecht
    191
    Poem by Elva for Joyce, 1974
    192
    Jean Warholic
    193
    Dix and Barbara Wayman
    194
    Margaret Werrell
    195
    Betty Whicher
    196
    Jeanne White
    197
    Sylvia Williams
    198
    Alene Wyatt
    199
    Emily Young, (2)
    201
    Shirley Young
    202
    Barbaba and Tony
    203
    Jane and Graham
    204
    Emoretta
    205
    Ann
    206
    Mary Louise
    207
    Levina [Marion?]
    208
    Georgia [Hewitt?]
    209
    Jinny
  - Documents generated by Joyce Hamilton Finch's death and funeral (Box 12, Folder 11)
    Documents include her obituary, "A Message from Joyce," and a transcript of the tribute to her by the Rev. David M. Evans, pastor of the First Baptist Church of Ithaca
  - Letters Herbert received, June-October 1991 (Box 12, Folder 12-16)
    While not technically Joyce's, these letters bear witness to the love people had for her and the impact she had on them. As with subseries two, the cards with no personal messages were not saved, the letters are arranged alphabetically and the sheets have been numbered. October was an arbitrary cut - off date
    Form letter reply
    3
    Kimberly Ackley
    Molly Adams
    6
    Kit and Haraln Banks
    7
    Dede and Tom Bennett
    Mart Berens
    Barbara and Christian Boissonnas
    Janet Bonebrake
    Ellen Bonn
    Jane Brentlinger
    Charlotte Bruce
    Sarah Brumberg
    17
    Rich Calkins
    18
    George and Ann Calvert
    19
    Peter Capalongo
    Adrienne and Tony Caputi
    22
    Amy Holman Casey
    Linda Caughey
    Betty Jo Cavanaugh
    25
    David and Linda Chapman
    Sandy and Martha Cheney
    27
    Pierre Clavel
    28
    Dale and Nellie Corson
    29
    Bob and Barbara Cotts
    Dave and Mary Curtiss
    31
    Peter and Pidge Curtiss
    Ginny Dankurt
    33
    Mary Don
    34
    Diane and Charlie Driscoll
    35
    36
    Shirley Edsall
    37
    Sanford (IvI) Eigenbrode
    Adam and Tony Engst
    Frances Farrell
    Trudy Firestone
    45
    Fran Fleming
    47
    Bill and Barbara Fry
    Dee Gardner
    Clara Golay
    Jim Goldman
    Mary Alice Grafton
    SElby Gration
    Rita Guerlac
    54
    Elaine Harris Hatch
    Barbara Hat
    Rita Healey
    Libby Hedrick
    Margaret Hobbie
    Martha Hodges
    Pat Seits-Peabody (Hospicare)
    62
    John and Martha Hsu
    63
    Carol Kammen
    Curtis K. Mooney (Ky Bapt)
    Sue Kilgore
    Frank and Karen Koroshec
    Barbara Kretzman
    Eva and John Kronik
    69
    Emula Lee
    70
    Joe and Ginny Leonard
    71
    Alicia and JOhn Lewkowicz
    72
    Laura Linke
    73
    Naomi Lowrance
    77
    78
    Jack Martin
    79
    Jane McCarthy
    Matt McHugh
    JIm and Carolyn McPherson
    Kay and Kim Milling
    Brad Mitchell
    Marg and Henry Murphy
    87
    Catherine Murray-Rust
    88
    Lee Nilson
    89
    John PArish (OBU)
    Olin Library Administration
    Betsy Ann Olive
    Jan Olsen
    Boyd and Peggy Pack
    Earl Peters
    Marica Samuelson Phillips
    96
    Louis and Lillian Pitschmann
    Sumi Prabhu
    Barbara and Ken Privett
    Joel Rabinowitz
    Howard Rolf
    Setsuko Reis
    105
    Peggy Sue Richards
    106
    Carol Roscoe
    John Roscos
    Pat Schafer
    Alain Seznec
    Betsy Shaw
    Bob Slowcum
    Willard and Janie Speck
    114
    Carolone Spicer
    115
    Neal Stamp
    Dorothy Staller
    Mildred Steinbaugh
    June Stone
    120
    David Stotz
    121
    Suzy Szasz
    Grace and Jack Tasler
    Ellen Thomas
    124
    Hershel and Louise Thompso n (2)
    Barney Unsworth
    Marjorie van de Poll
    Helen Vandervort
    Elva and Volbrecht
    Igna Wald
    Ruth and Dick Walker
    135
    Elizabeth S. Ward
    Karl Warren (poem)
    Dorothy Warren
    Rachel and David Yeh
    Liz Wilkinson
    Ben Williams
    Dave Williams
    Sylvia and Pierce Williams
    Wanda and Wayne York
  - Diaries, journals, documents and writings (Box 13)
    Hand written thoughts and observations written on various size note cards, note books and spiral binders. There are two entries from the early 1960's, but they basically begin in 1984 and there are frequently long gaps between a run of entries. The entries deal with her spiritual growth, dreams, a wall hanging she commissioned, a story she wrote to amuse Kathy on a trip to the Finch family reunion in 1989 and her fight with cancer. Minimal annotation is added in brackets if it was judged necessary and obvious spelling or typographical errors have been corrected. The book she edited on Allan H. Treman is included
  - Oct. 26, 1961, 1 page typed (Box 13)
    Just after talking with Dr. Greene, her gynecologist in Lexington,
    "Well, then what would you say the chances are?"
    "Not more than 50 percent. Not good at all. In another six months or so, you should consider adoption."
    I hung up the phone and stood looking out my kitchen window. It was not exactly a bleak or dreary day. The wind was cold, but the sky was clear and a couple of red roses were still blooming just next to a large group of mums, heavily loaded with buds. In spite of this, depression settled around my shoulders and the tears welled up -- and stopped, forming that lump in my throat. Even if it had been spring and the dry, brown grass had been a lush green, it would have meant little comfort. It is hard to face the fact that you and the man you love may not be able to create together a new life which takes on characteristics of each and draws you closer to each other. But self pity never drives away sorrow -- it seems to feed on gloom. There are others who, for one reason or another, face the opposite problem. A child to them is not a reason for rejoicing. Surely there will be a child whom we can love and provide for and as that love grows, it won't matter for very long (probably no longer than it takes to get one look at the child) that we are not the physical parents. I would not consider adoption until I knew that I could give a child the same love I would give to one I myself had born. Surely God will meet our needs, lift the feeling of depression and guide us into the completion of His will
  - Sept. 25, 1962 (Box 13)
    Douglas is four months old; the healthiest, happiest child you can imagine. It is just as his father told him the other night after we got home from church: we are so proud of him we are about to pop. He is such a good baby and just the one we needed. Already we have been blessed over and over again and we are thankful to God each day for giving us this particular child. We could not possibly love any child more and by the way they acted when we took him
  - Addendum (Box 13)
    We also talked about color and looked at colors in the space where it will hang taking note of carpet, tile in adjoining bath and a framed paper sculpture which shares the same hall.
    We talked about dyeing the yarn. Barbara uses two kinds of dye -- one for wool and linen and a different one for cotton. We talked about warp -- there will be two warps -- etc. Here I lost interest. I am impressed with what she knows, but what I like is the interaction with an artist who can take me into the creative process, allow me to add my bit and then produce something that is -- somehow -- uniquely both of us. [Transcription stopped at this point]
- Series III. Material relative to the labor history course Finch taught in the ILR School in the 1972-1980
  - Class Schedules, Syllabi, Grades and Evaluations, 1972-1980 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Lectures, Documents and Independent Studies (499) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Student research papers on various cities (Box 16, Folder 1)